Guide to the Burney-Lear Drawings
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Burney-Lear drawings collection
1800-1866
OSB MSS fd 59
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
(12 albums)
The collection contains more than 1,000 drawings, sketches and watercolors by Edward Francis Burney, other members of the Burney family, members of the Hoare family, James Pattison Cockburn, and Edward Lear.
Other Storage Formats: 6 file drawers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Louis W. Hill, Jr., 1985.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCHES
Edward Francis Burney, a cousin of Fanny Burney, was born in Worcester in 1760. In 1776 he moved to London, where he studied at the Royal Academy Schools and gained the friendship of Sir Joshua Reynolds. He exhibited at the Royal Academy from 1780-1803. In 1784 he designed large illustrations for Dr. Charles Burney's volume for the Handel commemoration at Westminster Abbey. Burney is known for his large satirical watercolors and caricatures. For the last forty years of his life, he worked almost exclusively as a book illustrator, illustrating the works of such poets as Langhorne and Young. E. F. Burney died in London in 1848.
James Pattison Cockburn was born in 1778. He was a pupil of P. Sandby's at Woolich, which he entered in 1793 and left in 1795 to serve at the capture of the Cape of Good Hope. After the peace of 1815 he was stationed for a time at Malta, and made a number of visits to Italy and Switzerland. He wrote and illustrated several books about his travels, including The Route of the Simplon (1822) and The Valley of the Austa (1823). He also visited Canada. He was Director of the Royal Laboratory, Woolich, from 1838 to 1846, and died at Woolich in 1849.
Sir Richard Colt Hoare was born in 1758. Between 1785 and 1791 he traveled on the Continent, filling a portfolio with drawings of interesting sights and objects, toured Monmouthshire with Archdeacon Coxe, and contributed sixty-three drawings to his friend's description of that county. Hoare was a member of the Royal Society and the Society of Antiquaries. He was particularly interested in the history and antiquities of his own county, and wrote and illustrated a variety of works on Wiltshire. His History of Modern Wiltshire was left unfinished when he died at Stourhead in 1838.
Edward Lear was born in London in 1812. In 1831 he was employed by the Zoological Society, assisting several scholars in their ornithological drawings. From 1832 to 1836 he was engaged at Knowsley, the residence of the Earl of Derby, and drew the plates to The Knowsley Menagerie. Lear invented his Book of Nonsense for his patron's grandchildren. Beginning in 1836 he devoted himself to landscape, and in 1837 he left England, returning only for brief visits. He was a drawing master in Rome for several years. He also traveled in Southern Europe, Palestine, and India, and published several illustrated journeys of his tours. He began to exhibit at the Royal Academy in 1850. Edward Lear spent the last few years of his life in San Remo, where he died in January 1888.
Scope and Contents
The Burney-Lear Drawings consists of over 1,000 watercolors, sketches, and drawings by Edward Francis Burney, other members of the Burney family, members of the Hoare family, Edward Lear, and others. Most of the drawings are unsigned, and some of the attributions are still uncertain. The majority of the material appears to date from the first half of the nineteenth century.
The collection originally consisted of eight bound albums and three portfolios of unbound drawings. Both albums and portfolios carry numbers assigned to them by Charles J. Sawyer before the sale of the collection to Louis W. Hill, Sr. Sawyer's numbering sequence has been retained, but the unbound drawings have been removed from the three portfolios and placed in one box and six oversize containers. Individual unbound drawings have been given numbers, as have the leaves of the bound albums.
The largest group of drawings in the collection is related to the Burney family. About 200 drawings by Edward Francis Burney, the watercolorist and book illustrator, can be found in Albums 4 and 5a. These include designs for illustrations and studies for larger works. Album 5a also contains works by other members of the E. F. Burney family, including his brother, Thomas Frederick Burney, and his sister, Elizabeth Warren Burney. Albums 1, 5b, and 8 house additional drawings attributed to various members of the Burney family. Landscapes predominate, but there are also several Burney family portraits.
Albums 6 and 7 are almost certainly associated with the family of Sir Richard Colt Hoare, and Albums 2 and 3 may be also. These albums contain much amateur work, although there are some interesting views. The watercolors in Albums 2 and 3 may be by the same hand, and it has been suggested that their style recalls that of Samuel Prout or of George Barret the younger.
The last three albums contain work by unrelated artists. There are approximately forty-five landscape sketches by Edward Lear in Album 11. Many of these are identified, annotated, and dated views of Mediterranean scenes. Album 9 houses sepia-wash landscapes attributed to Major-General James Pattison Cockburn. Finally, Album 10 is the sketchbook of an unidentified amateur.
Album 12, the 1986 gift of Louis W. Hill, Jr., contains 127 watercolor sketches and drawings, many attributed to Edward Lear.
The Burney-Lear Drawings are of considerable interest to students of Edward Lear, Edward Francis Burney, and the Burney family in general. Several of the views, such as the scenes of Brighton in Album 1, have some historical value. In addition, the many amateur landscapes provide excellent documentation of the development of the picturesque in England.
Drawing; Painters -- Great Britain; Watercolor painting; Devon (England); England -- Description and travel; Wiltshire (England); Artists; Illustrators; Burney, Edward Francis, 1760-1848; Cockburn, James Pattison, 1779?-1847; Hoare, Richard Colt, Sir, 1758-1838; Lear, Edward, 1812-1888
- Album List
  - Leaves numbered 1-41. Many juvenile drawings of Italian scenes, possibly by members of Charles Parr Burney's family. Also English scenes by several hands, including two views of Brighton ca. 1813 and a rural scene in black and white chalk (31). (Box 1)
  - Leaves numbered 1-273. Inscribed "Arabella Hoare, July 1866." Watercolors and sepia-wash drawings showing scenes in the West of England and the Isle of Wight. Subjects include the gardens and grounds at Stourhead, the home of Sir Richard Colt Hoare. The style of the watercolors resembles that of George Barret the younger. Many are dated, mostly between 1800 and 1820. (Box 2)
  - Leaves numbered 1-206. Inscribed "Sophia's." Watercolors and sepia-wash drawings, mostly of scenes in Devonshire; many of Torquay, Teignmouth, and Sidmouth. Attributed to the watercolorist of Album 2. Several sketches the pencil initials, which may be "JB" or "GB." Dates range from 1803 to 1836, with the majority after 1820. (Box 3)
  - 124 small unmounted drawings in pencil, sepia, and colored chalk, 121 by Edward Francis Burney. They include sketches for book illustrations (some marked "used" and "unused"), studies for a group of astrological paintings, and designs for front pieces and vignettes. (Box 4)
  - 75 unmounted works, 28 of which are by Edward Francis Burney. Among these are more sketches for the astrological group, and a study in thin oils for The Rape of the Lock (134). Most of the remaining drawings are attributed to other members of the Burney family, such as Edward Kaye Burney, Thomas Frederick Burney, and Edward Warren Burney. They include views, life studies, and several family portraits. There is a watercolor of Camilla Cottage. Drawing 143 is a portrait sketch of Frances and Arabella Hoare. (Box 5a-b)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Oversize album 5a, drawings 1-25 and album 5b, drawings 1-32.
  - Leaves numbered 1-27. Volumes of 92 watercolors and pencil sketches, probably by members of the Hoare family. Figure studies and landscapes, including several of Glastonbury Abbey. There are pencil initials on or below nearly all of the drawings, such as "RPH," "PH," "RCH," and "RGF," all in the same hand. (Box 6)
  - Leaves numbered 1-47. Volume of watercolors, wash-drawings, and pencil drawings by various members of the Hoare family, according to pencil annotations on the album pages. There are also initials found in Album 6. Also contains prints, including a caricature by George Moutard Woodward. (Box 7)
  - Pages numbered 1-58. Burney family album, containing about 6 drawings by E.F. Burney (signed "E.F.B.") including a scene from Cecelia. Many of the watercolors and sketches bear the initials of other Burney family members, including Elizabeth Warren Burney and Thomas Frederick Burney. A watercolor of the Thrale villa at Streatham is mounted on page 4. (Box 8)
  - Leaves numbered 1-56. Landscape drawings in sepia-wash by Major-General James Pattison Cockburn, including views of the Simplon, the Grande Chartreuse, Crevola, and Mount Cenis. Titles beneath the sketches, with some pencil annotations on the album pages. (Box 9)
  - Leaves numbered 1-26. Sketchbook inscribed "Miss Tanner. Lockridge, Wilts. June 1820." Pencil sketches, mostly of county seats in Wiltshire, including two of Fonthill Abbey and three of Stourhead. Also a few sketches of views on the Isle of Wight. Some sketches dated, 1820-25. (Box 10)
  - Several portraits and silhouettes of Burney family members, including Clara and Emma Burney and Mrs. James Burney. (Note: this portfolio originally held a preliminary drawing for E. F. Burney's Amateurs of Tye-Wig Music. That drawing has been transferred to the Yale Center for British Art.) A group of large unmounted drawings, approximately 45 of which are by Edward Lear. There are landscape sketches, some on blue or brown paper, in ink over pencil and in pencil. Many are identified, dated, and annotated for color by Lear. Subjects include Tintern Abbey, Windsor, and a variety of Mediterranean scenes. Dates range from 1836 to 1866, with many drawings dated 1866. (Box 11)
    See: Oversize, album 11.
- Oversize
  - These boxes contain the remaining contents of album 5a, and the entire album 5b. (Box 5a-b)
  - This box contains the entire contents of album 11. (Box 11)
- 1986 Addition to the Burney-Lear Drawings Collection
  - Album. Leaves numbered 1-71. Scrapbook labeled "Lear." 127 drawings, watercolors, and sketches, many attributed to Edward Lear. (Box 12)